Guide to the Hendrik Willem van Loon papers, 1884-1972.
Van Loon, Hendrick Willem papers,
- Series VII. Memorabilia
  - Subseries VIIa. Scrapbooks, guest books, photograph albums and photographs, notebooks, diaries, passports, pamphlets, certificates, diplomas, phonograph records, games, puzzles, and miscellaneous.
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon and "Jimmie" travel photos Middleburg photos pictures and postal cards from photos, [4x5] [duplicates ] (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Photos of: "Jimmie" Hendrik Willem van Loon Hendrik Willem van Loon with family: Janet Hall, Henry Bowditch Van Loon, unidentified, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified carte-des-visites, [4x5] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon childhood photos, ca. 1884-1892 carte-des-visites cabinet cards picture of parents (1 picture possibly of Hendrik Willem van Loon's mother Elisabeth Johanna Hanken), [5x7] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon in "Nieuw Veere" photographs in Veere, Holland, [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous small photos, 1934-1938; [5x7] [duplicates ] [negative] (Box 58, Folder 10)
      Includes: gravesite of Elisabeth Johanna 1904 (neg.) Hendrik Willem van Loon in costume (postal card) Hendrik Willem van Loon in South Seas (Franconia Cruise) 1934 Hendrik Willem van Loon and "Jimmie" aboard ship Eliza Bowditch photo Ruth/Helen Hoffman (twins) photos and postal cards Hendrik Willem van Loon on sun deck of S.S. Nieuw Veere, Jan. 23, 1938 Elisabeth Johanna Hanken
    - Criswell Family pictures: Martha Emily McKee Criswell, [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - Criswell Family pictures: John T. Criswell, [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous pictures of Hendrik Willem van Loon's relatives class pictures of Hendrik Willem van Loon pictures of Dorset, VT Ruby Fuhr photos, [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 13)
    - Pictures of JCVL (with Noodle, Meisel, and her parents), [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - Post card views, [5x7] (Box 58, Folder 15)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon with President Medina of Venezuala, 1944 photo and correspondence from William LaVarne Hendrik Willem van Loon's 60th birthday party (at "Nieuw Veere"), 1942, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous photos, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 17)
      includes: Suus with her two boys, Wimmie and Janneman, from The Hague, Holland, 1920 aboard the R.M.S. "Franconia," Jan. 1934 Dutch relatives in native costume: color print of Jo and Hein Verlinde, 1959 in Veere black and white of Jo and Hein Verlinde in Veere 1 other, 1905 Hendrik Willem van Loon fresco at "De Houtuin" in Veere, Holland Hendrik Willem van Loon at a dinner Hendrik Willem van Loon and unidentified man commemorative plaque at "De Houtuin" (duplicate)
    - "Information Please" and publicity photos with Elsie the Cow, cancer committee dinner photo with Lady Armstrong, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 18)
    - "Information Please" and publicity photos, [8x10] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 19)
    - Washington Square West photos, c. 1932 interior of Holley Chambers c. 1932 photo with Noodle, [8x10] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 20)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon portraits, 1906-1940; [8x10] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 21)
      Cornell 1906 graduation picture with various annotations Erasmus statue Hendrik Willem van Loon with soldier figurines, Old Greenwich, Conn., 1940 portrait painting of Hendrik Willem van Loon (by Joseph Groin) portrait painting of Hendrik Willem van Loon Hendrik Willem van Loon poses (2 in "Nieuw Veere") Hendrik Willem van Loon poses with violin
    - Graduation picture from Cornell, 1902 several photos with Noodle, [8x10] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 22)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon at the typewriter Hendrik Willem van Loon at the microphone at WVRL, NY, 1943, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 23)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon poses (1 with Mungo, c. 1942), [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 24)
    - Graphic illustrations of Hendrik Willem van Loon, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 25)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon and sons (Gerard and Henry Bowditch) "Jimmie" photos, 1923, 1927, 1933, and others including 1922 (Ithaca, NY), 1932, 1941 photos, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 26)
    - Launching of Liberty Ship "Hendrik Willem van Loon", 1945, [8x10] [duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 27)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon and friends, including: Eleanor Roosevelt, Westbrook Pegler, Sir Charles Kingsford-Smith, Ross Skinner, Lucie van Dam Van Isselt, J.W. Perrels, Rene (Lorena Gibbs) Godfrey Scudamore (Box 58, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous large photos: postal cards, several views of Middleburg, rendering of the Criswell Home, Eleanor M. Lanyon, JCVL, Raymond Gram Swing, [8x10] (Box 58, Folder 29)
    - Friends, includes: Henri Mayer, 1932; Frits Phillips; Dr. Alice Bernheim; Dr. Charles Koch, 1932, Middleburg; Rene (Lorena Gibbs) Godfrey Scudamore, Paris, 1931, OS (Box 58, Folder 30)
    - "Jimmie", 1931, 1932 and undated Hendrik Willem van Loon and Gerard, 1931, Veere Hendrik Willem van Loon on bicycle Hendrik Willem van Loon with Ten Klooster (artist) on the Kade in Veere, 1931 (Isle Bing, photographer) reverse negative print, OS[duplicates] (Box 58, Folder 31)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon, 1930, 1932, 1936, c. 1942 with Mungo, with Erasmus, with violin, and others, OS (Box 58, Folder 32)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon studio portraits, c. 1913, OS (Box 58, Folder 33-34)
    - Photographic reproductions, Os (Box 58, Folder 35)
    - Duplicate photos, OS (Box 58, Folder 36)
    - June 13, 1935, WJZ, 3 records, R49-R51 (Box 59)
    - Sept. 26, 1935, NBC, "Music is My Hobby," 2 records, R32 (Box 59)
    - May 11, 1940, NBC, "Council Against Intolerance", 2 records, R48 (Box 59)
    - Nov. 10, 1940, "Let's Face Facts", 4 records, R27-R30 (Box 59)
    - 1941-1942, Nederlandsche feestmarsch, R37 (Box 59)
    - April 19, 1942, WABC, "Freedom", R52 (Box 59)
    - Nov. 18, 1942, WOR, "Cresta Blanca Carnival," 2 records, R45-R46 (Box 59)
    - Dec. 24, 1942, WNCA, "Christmas Eve Message", R53 (Box 59)
    - June 14, 1944, "JCVL, Launching of the ship 'Hendrik Willem van Loon'", R38 (Box 59)
    - May 26, ?, WJZ, R47 (Box 59)
    - Dr. N.A.C. Slotemaker de Bruine, R36 (Box 59)
    - "Heritage", R34 (Box 59)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon's Suite by Furcell, Bach Society, R33 (Box 59)
    - "Music You Want", 2 copies, R35 (Box 59)
    - 7 unidentified records, R31, R36-R44 (Box 59)
    - 18 Talking Book Records, "The Arts" (Box 89)
    - Bells of The Spanish Armada (Box 89)
    - The Liberty Bell (Box 89)
    - NBC Broadcasts: Dec. 28, 1937 Jan. 5, 1938 (Box 89)
    - WQXR Broadcast; Sept. 15, 1939 (Box 89)
    - 35 mm film of Hendrik Willem van Loon speaking on League of Nations and an "Economic League of Nations" c. 1939, F. 169
    - Sound for movie film F. 169, TR. 1716a, TR. 1863
    - Copy of film reel 934., V-384
    - Microfilm reels (Box 70-73)
  - Subseries VIIb. Collected memorabilia includes various miscellaneous documents, volumes, and reprints collected by van Loon.
    - The Companionate Marriage (Box 34)
    - Volume, La Constitution Francaise, Paris 1791 (Box 34)
    - Volume, (bound in vellum) Eleytheria Sive De Manumissione, Wilhelmo a Loon, 1685 (Box 34)
    - 1 sketch (Box 59)
    - 3 travel posters (Box 59)
    - 3 prints (Box 59)
    - Portfolios: Rembrandt's Etswerk met Tekst van Jhr. Dr. Six, reprints of sketches and portraits (Box 60-61)
    - 2 Bible Almanacs, 1832 and 1852, written in Dutch (in envelopes addressed to Dr. L. Ries) (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - W. Fiske bookplate (Box 62, Folder 2-3)
    - Copper engraved etching plate (Box 62, Folder 4-5)
    - Evelyn Rusby poems and music scores (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - Dante memorabilia (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - Collected photographs (Box 62, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 62, Folder 9)
    - The Newbery Medal for 1921 (by appointment only)
- Series VIII. Papers of Helen Criswell "Jimmie" van Loon
  Papers of Helen Cromwell "Jimmie" van Loon include an original play, diaries, "Mad Hatter Mutterings," and other miscellaneous material.
  - "Sixty Days of Sunshine" (a play, 2 copies) (Box 63, Folder 1-7)
  - "Mad Hatter Mutterings", April 1920- July 1921 (Box 63, Folder 8-28)
  - Pamphlets (Box 63, Folder 29)
  - List of vocabulary words in English, Dutch and Italian (Box 63, Folder 30)
  - The Annie Wright Seminary (Box 63, Folder 31)
  - WCBS broadcast, March 1, 1947 (Box 63, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 63, Folder 33)
  - Bible belonging to Eliza Helen Criswell given to Gerard Willem Van Loon (Box 63, Folder 34)
  - 40 diaries dated 1921-1954 (Box 64)
  - 1 folder containing certificates and documents (Box 64)
- Series IX. Papers of Gerard Willem van Loon
  Papers of Gerard Willem van Loon includes drafts and photos for his biography about Hendrik Willem van Loon, and correspondence pertaining to his father and the manuscript.
  - Subseries IXa. Drafts
    - The Story of Hendrik Willem Van Loon was originally entitled Hendrik Willem Van Loon: A Portrait in Paradox
    - Original photos and art work from The Story of Hendrik Willem Van Loon by Gerard Willem Van Loon can be found in Box 50
    - The Story of Hendrik Willem Van Loon by Gerard Willem Van Loon, interviews and obituaries (Box 65, Folder 1-8)
    - Carbon of The Story of Hendrik Willem Van Loon (Box 65, Folder 9-19)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon quotations from books (Box 65, Folder 20-27)
    - Draft copy of The Story of Hendrik Willem Van Loon (Box 65, Folder 28-60)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon quotations from letters checklist (Box 65, Folder 61-73)
  - Subseries IXb. Correspondence
    - A-Fraser Bond (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Boni-Brumbaugh (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Katherine Mygatt (Bright) (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Grace Castagnetta (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - C (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - Mary Lewis Chapman (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - D (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - E-F (Box 66, Folder 8)
    - G (Box 66, Folder 9)
    - H (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - Francis Hackett (Box 66, Folder 11)
    - Lorena Hickock (Box 66, Folder 12)
    - Ruth/Helen Hoffman (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - Fanny Hurst (Box 66, Folder 14)
    - J-L (Box 66, Folder 15)
    - Library of Congress (Box 66, Folder 16)
    - Joop Meijlinck-Hanken (cousin Jopie) (Box 66, Folder 17)
    - Professor Bayard Quincy Morgan (Box 66, Folder 18)
    - M (Box 66, Folder 19)
    - N-P (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Waldo Peirce (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - June Hamilton Rhodes (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - R-Sears (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - Shimkin-Spingarn (Box 67, Folder 5)
    - Stadtoberinspektor-Swing (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Peter Schwartzkopff (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Richard Simon (Box 67, Folder 8)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (Box 67, Folder 9)
    - Elsie Spiess (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - Lucy Tal (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - T (Box 67, Folder 12)
    - Margaret Valiant (Box 67, Folder 13)
    - Tonia van Rijn van Alkemade (Box 67, Folder 14)
    - Suus van Loon van der Hilst (tante Suus) (Box 67, Folder 15-16)
    - Van Der Veen-Van Loon (Box 67, Folder 17)
    - Van Paasen-Von Muller (Box 67, Folder 18)
    - (Tante) von Trischke (Box 67, Folder 19)
    - W-Z and unidentified (Box 67, Folder 20)
  - Subseries IXc. Visual Materials
    - Seven slides, which include: (Box 67, Folder 21)
    - Portrait of Hendrik Willem van Loon by Leon Gordon, painted in Veere, Holland, 1932 (unfinished) (Box 67, Folder 21)
    - Bakastraat der Haag, April 1961 (3 slides) (Box 67, Folder 21)
    - Utaw Place in Baltimore, photographed in 1966 just after the house in which Hendrik Willem van Loon and "Jimmie" lived had been torn down (Box 67, Folder 21)
    - Newbery Award medal made by George Brewer in Detroit at the annual American Library Association meeting, July, 1965 (2 slides) (Box 67, Folder 21)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books written or illustrated by Van Loon, including foreign translations, catalogued separately.